Christopher Dienes

Statistician | Data Scientist

Contact
Information

Phone: E-mail:

Website: chrisdienes.github.io

OVERVIEW

Statistician with strong academic background, diverse skill set, high attention to detail, enjoys both mentoring and consulting, successful leading projects, and ability to communicate complex concepts to audiences of all levels.

AREAS OF SPECIALIZATION Applied and mathematical statistics, Bayesian statistics, data visualization, machine learning, statistical computing, big data, data collection and manipulation, surveys, time series, teaching, applications include (but not limited to) business, economics, health care, environmental sciences, and sports. Leadership skills include situational leadership training.

Computer Skills LATEX, Linux/Windows, MATLab, MongoDB, Python, R, R Shiny, SAS, Spark, SQL, Tableau, Web Design (HTML/CSS/JavaScript).

Professional Experience

Seagate Technology

Staff Data Scientist

February 2016 - Present

- Internal consultant on projects spanning the data science field, including algorithm development, data visualization, big data computing, storage, and applied statistics.
- Leads internal training by hosting monthly methodology reading group and contributes to internal analytics website through curriculum, blog posts, and Q&A forums.
- Open source classification project: https://github.com/ChrisDienes/SeaClass.
- Current Salary:

Senior Data Scientist

February 2015 - January 2016

- Team lead for algorithm development, machine learning, data visualization, and anomaly detection; primarily focused on creating software applications for storage device systems.
- Contact:

Harris Corporation/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention

Data Analyst 3

July 2014 - January 2015

- Federal contractor for the CDC National Center for Health Statistics. Work included statistical consulting, machine learning, data visualization, and survey topics. Designed and led a data disclosure project involving high frequency physical activity monitors.
- Contact:

University of California - Davis

Graduate Student Employment

2008 - 2013

• Associate Instructor: Led five undergraduate courses covering topics in elementary statistics, probability theory, and time series analysis.

- Teaching Assistant: Assisted lead professors with tasks related to administering college level courses.
- Research Assistant: Assisted collaborative project on corporative rankings in hierarchical networks. Duties included data manipulation, analysis and presentation of findings.
- Contact:

EDUCATION

University of California - Davis

Ph.D., Statistics, September 2013

- Dissertation Topic: On-line monitoring in time series models.
- Pre-Qualifying Exam: 94% (Theoretical), 97% (Quantitative)
- GPA: 4.0
- Advisor: Alexander Aue

M.S., Statistics, March 2011

Montana Tech of the University of Montana

B.S., Mathematics, May 2008

- Minor: Business Administration
- GPA: 4.0

Papers

Dienes, C. (2017, Submitted). The low-rank hurdle model.

Aue, A., C. Dienes, S. Fremdt, and J. G. Steinebach (2015). Reaction times of monitoring schemes for ARMA time series. *Bernoulli*. Vol. 21, No. 2, 1238-1259.

Dienes, C., and A. Aue (2014). On-line monitoring of pollution concentrations with autoregressive moving average time series. *Journal of Time Series Analysis*. Vol. 35, Issue 3, 239-261.

Honors and Awards

Montana Tech Alumni Recognition Award, 2015

Harris Corp URock Award, 2014

UC Davis Department of Statistics Service Award, 2013

UC Davis Outstanding Graduate Student Teaching Award, 2012

UC Davis Statistics Graduate Student of the Year (Julius Blum Award), 2010

Montana Tech Undergraduate Valedictorian, 2008

Goldwater Scholarship, 2007

Montana Tech Chancellor's Honor Roll (4.0 required), 2004-8

Marie M. Moebus Presidential Scholarship, 2004

Browning High School Valedictorian, 2004

Montana High School Honors Scholarship, 2004

Interests

Art, Dogs, Games, Golf, Music, Nature, Trivia